all right
[Music]
in my last video I featured a study that
found that curtailing sleep can cut your
rate of body fat loss in half while
exacerbating the loss of lean mass
to get better insight into what was
going on researchers took fat and muscle
biopsies from people after a night of
sleep loss in terms of genes that were
turned on and off molecular signatures
were discovered suggesting muscle
breakdown and fat buildup that was after
an all-nighter though and in the weight
loss study the Sleep restricted groups
ended up getting a little more than five
hours a night what about a more
realistic scenario like sleeping just
one hour less a night
overweight adults were randomized to
eight weeks of a calorie restricted diet
or the same diet combined with just five
days a week of one hour a night less
sleep the Sleep restricted group
achieved the one hour day less sleep on
weekdays but ended up sleeping an hour
more on the weekend day so overall they
just cut about three hours of sleep out
of their week with just those few hours
a week made any weight loss difference
on the scale no but in the normal sleep
group eighty percent of the weight loss
was fat whereas in the group just
missing a few hours of sleep a week it
was the opposite eighty percent of the
loss was lean this shows that a few
hours of ketchup sleep on the weekends
is insufficient and May in fact be
contributing to the problem based on the
social jet lag effect I explored in a
previous video
a comparable study was designed for kids
but the sleeping periods only lasted a
week 8 to 11 year olds were randomized
to either increase or decrease their
time in bed by one and a half hours per
night for a week then switch the
following week they had an average of
134 calories more on the days they slept
less and gained in that week about half
a pound compared to the sleep more week
the question then becomes would sleeping
more facilitate weight loss when it
comes to body fat can we just sleep it
off
the benefit of Interventional studies is
you can demonstrate cause and effect but
observational studies can allow you to
more easily track people in their
behaviors over a longer time span for
example research has followed a group of
mostly overweight individuals who
started out to averaging less than six
hours of sleep a night for more than
five years during that time about a half
maintained that schedule but the other
have increased their sleep duration up
to seven or eight hours a night ended up
gaining five pounds less fat
are studying to have sleeping habits
predict the magnitude of fat loss among
those cutting calories found that every
extra hour of sleep at night was
associated with an extra one and a half
pounds of weight loss over a period of
about three to six months that's not the
same as randomizing people's extra sleep
though I mean maybe they're sleeping
more because they were exercising more
and that's the real reason they lost
more weight
getting people to bump their sleep from
five and a half hours up to seven can
lead to an overall decrease in appetite
within two weeks particularly for sugar
and salty foods a four week study
getting habitual short sleepers to sleep
an extra hour at night let them to
consume about two fewer spoonfuls of
sugar a day compared to the control
group but this didn't translate into any
changes in body composition a 12-week
study on the other hand randomized the
overweight and obese individuals to a
weight loss intervention with or without
a sleep component found that the Sleep
group lost weight significantly faster
a national cross-sectional survey
suggested lower obesity rates among kids
and households that regularly ate dinner
together as a family got adequate sleep
and limited screen times and so Harvard
researchers decided to try to put those
behaviors to the test
a six-month randomized trial to improve
household routines for obesity
prevention among young children resulted
in a lower BMI normally it's hard to
tease out the effects of multi-component
interventions but in this case
exhortation is to limit overall TV
watching didn't work and the families
were already eating together six days a
week and so that didn't change much
either the only thing they were able to
get the kids to significantly alter was
their sleep and so the improved weight
outcomes may be attributed at least in
part to the three-quarters of an hour
average increase in nightly sleep
overall most sleep Improvement
interventions tended to show improved
weight loss I was intrigued to look up
the one study that didn't the nice thing
about systematic reviews as opposed to
so-called narrative reviews is that they
exhaustively include mention of every
study that meets some pre-specified
criteria this keeps reviewers from
cherry picking but it can also lead to
the inclusion of some strange studies in
this case a randomized controlled trial
of did you redo playing the indigenous
Australian wind instrument those
randomized to the didgeridoo to improve
their Sleep Quality did not lose any
weight but they also failed to improve
the quality of their sleep or likely
that of their neighbors
foreign